# **Mohammad Sabik Irbaz**

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/sabik-irbaz/ Twitter: twitter.com/msi\_bertman Portfolio: msi1427.github.io/ Email: sabikirbaz@iut-dhaka.edu GitHub: github.com/msi1427 Phone: +8801623848732

Last updated December 14, 2021

I am a Data Scientist at Leadbook Pte. Ltd. I am currently working with Dr. Md. Ruhul Amin from Fordham University on data-driven Social NLP problems. I used to work as a Lead ML Engineer at Omdena Inc. and Pioneer Alpha Ltd. where I have led several ML projects from research, development to production. During my four years of undergraduate studies, I was immensely fortunate to be advised by Dr. Md. Kamrul Hasan and Dr. Hasan Mahmud where I have mostly worked on Text Style Transfer (TST), Clinical ML, and Data-centric AI.

### **Research Interests**

I am primarily excited about Natural Language Processing (NLP), Artificial Intelligence (AI), Computational Social Science, and Data Science research. My research interests include:

- Efficient modeling, benchmarking, evaluation and robustness in NLP [P5, P6]
- Annotating and cleaning datasets with minimal cost [P5, P8]
- Fact verification using historical data [P7]
- Explainable, Interpretable, and Reproducible AI
- Low-resource and Multilingual NLP [P3, P4]
- AI for Good (Social, Clinical & Other Disciplines) [P1, P2, P5, P6, P7]

### **Education**

## Islamic University of Technology(IUT)

Dhaka, Bangladesh Jan, 2017 - Mar, 2021

B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE)

**CGPA**: 3.44/4.00

Dissertation: "Medical Expertise Style Transfer using Denoising Autoencoders" [Thesis Book] [Presentation]

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Kamrul Hasan and Dr. Hasan Mahmud

Notre Dame College(NDC)

Dhaka, Bangladesh GPA: **5.00**/5.00 Jul, 2014 - Dec, 2016

Cox's Bazar Government High School

Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh

Secondary Secondary Certificate (SSC), 2014

Higher Secondary Certificate (HSC), 2016

GPA: **5.00**/5.00 Jan, 2009 - Dec, 2013

## **Research Experience**

 $\{^{\alpha}$  primary contributor;  $^{\beta}$  secondary contributor;  $^{\gamma}$  supervisor $\}$ 

# Fordham Human Centered AI Research Lab

Mar, 2021 - Present

Department of CIS, Fordham University, New York, USA

Advisor(s): Dr. Md. Ruhul Amin

- (1) °COVID-19 Public Policy Conformity Analysis NLP, Data Extraction, Topic Modeling, NLI, EDA [P7]
- (2) <sup>\alpha</sup> Mitigating Social Bias in NLP NLP, Explainability, Text Style Transfer

## Computer Vision Lab (CVLab)

Nov, 2020 - Present

Department of CSE, IUT, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Advisor(s): Sabbir Ahmed

- (1) <sup>\alpha</sup> Automatic Radiology Report Generation *NLP, Image Captioning, Image Segmentation* [Report]
- (2) <sup>7</sup>Data-centric Approach for Explainabile Text Classification NLP, Active Learning, Explainability
- (3) <sup>7</sup>Logical Reasoning QA using Standardized Test Questions NLP, QA, CSR, Data Collection, NLI

## Systems and Software Lab (SSL)

Jul, 2019 - Present

Department of CSE, IUT, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Advisor(s): Dr. Md. Kamrul Hasan, Dr. Hasan Mahmud

- (1)  $^{\beta}$  Automated wheelchairs for semi-paralyzed patients. Signal Processing, ML, Adruino
- (2) "Medical Expertise Text Style Transfer NLP, Active Learning, Text Style Transfer [P5, P6]
- (3) <sup>\alpha</sup> Efficient Active Learning Approach for Data Annotation ML, Active Learning, Data Annotation [P8]
- (4) Query-focused Multi-Document Text Summarization for Bangla NLP, Low-resource QA, Summarization
- (5) <sup>\alpha</sup>Trustworthy NLP NLP, Out-of-domain Data Filtering

### **Publications**

More updated list here or Google Scholar {\*equal contribution, <sup>c</sup>corresponding author}

- [P8] **Mohammad Sabik Irbaz**, Raian Rahman, Hasan Mahmud, and Md. Kamrul Hasan<sup>c</sup>. "Efficient Active Learning Approach for Data Annotation". *Manuscript in Preparation*.
- [P7] **Mohammad Sabik Irbaz**, Md. Ruhul Amin<sup>c</sup>, Rupak Sarkar, and Ashiqur R. KhudaBukhsh. "**COVID-19 Public Policy Conformity Analysis**". *Manuscript in Preparation*. [Presentation]
- [P6] **Mohammad Sabik Irbaz**, Abir Azad, Raian Rahman, Hasan Mahmud, and Md. Kamrul Hasan<sup>c</sup>. "**Medical Expertise Style Transfer using Denoising Autoencoders**". *Manuscript in Preparation*. [Book]
- [P5] Mohammad Sabik Irbaz, Abir Azad, Zarif Ahmed, Md. Ashfaq Raiyan, Raian Rahman, Hasan Mahmud, and Md. Kamrul Hasan<sup>c</sup>. "c-MSD: A Curated Dataset for Medical Expertise Style Transfer using Active Learning Approach". *Under Review*.
- [P4] Alif Ashrafee\*, Akib Mohammed Khan\*, **Mohammad Sabik Irbaz**<sup>c</sup>, and MD Abdullah Al Nasim. **"Real-time Bangla License Plate Recognition Pipeline for Low Resource Video-based Applications"**. *Real-World Surveillance: Applications and Challenges Workshop, collocated with IEEE/CVF WACV 2022* [Presentation] [Poster]
- [P3] Fahim Shahriar Khan, Mueeze Al Mushabbir, **Mohammad Sabik Irbaz**<sup>c</sup>, and MD Abdullah Al Nasim. "End-to-End Natural Language Understanding Pipeline for Bangla Conversational Agents". Proceedings of the 20<sup>th</sup> IEEE International Conference on Machine Learning and Applications, 2022 [Presentation]
- [P2] Mohammad Sabik Irbaz<sup>c</sup>, MD Abdullah Al Nasim, and Refat E Ferdous. "Real-Time Face Recognition System for Remote Employee Tracking". Proceedings of the International Conference on Big Data, IoT, and Machine Learning, 2022. Springer, Singapore.
- [P1] Mohammad Sabik Irbaz\*, Abir Azad\*, Tanjila Alam Sathi, and Lutfun Nahar Lota<sup>c</sup>. "Nurse Care Activity Recognition Based on Machine Learning Techniques Using Accelerometer Data". Proceedings of the 8<sup>th</sup> International Workshop on Human Activity Sensing Corpus and Applications, collocated with ACM UbiComp/ISWC 2020 [DOI] [Presentation]

## **Industry Experience**

Leadbook Pte. Ltd.

Singapore

**Data Scientist** 

Dec, 2021 - Present

We have millions of contacts in our database. An important problem is to cluster contact job titles into categories in an unsupervised or semi-supervised manner. Most of my works involves improving and maintaining this pipeline. The project involves — NLP, Data Cleaning, Clustering, Phrase Similarity [Code]

Omdena Inc.

New York, USA

**Lead Machine Learning Engineer** 

Apr, 2021 - Jun, 2021

Collaborated with 50 ML and data engineers from 20 countries on **Equilo Project** - Building Gender Equality Assessment Functionality using NLP. This large scale work was divided into 7 major tasks. I was the **task leader** of the team building the **recommender system** for the organizations with low gender equality scores. I also lead the team building the web app and deploying the whole data and ML pipeline to **GCP**.

This project involved — Scraping, NLP, GCP, Firestore, Django, ReactJS, StreamLit, Cloud SQL [Article]

# Pioneer Alpha Ltd.

Dhaka, Bangladesh Jan, 2021 - Oct, 2021

Lead Machine Learning Engineer

- Supervised and delivered the following core projects successfully to the corresponding clients:
  (1) Multilingual Chatbot as Business Assistant *NLP*, *NLU*, *Low-resource*, *Tensorflow*, *Rasa*, *Flask* [Code] [P3]
- (2) Low-resource Bangla License Plate Detection and Recognition OCR, Tensorflow, OCR, Flask [Code] [P4]
- (3) Face Detection and Recognition for Remote Office Vision, OpenCV, dlib, Flask [P2]
- (4) Trello Automation for Directed Premiere Video Editing Vision, OpenCV, dlib, Adobe Premiere, Trello [Code]

### Nascenia Ltd.

#### Software Engineer, Intern

Dhaka, Bangladesh Nov, 2019 - Jan, 2020

Worked on a large-scale government project on VAT automation, Project Uddogi

This project involved — Ruby on Rails, HTML, CSS, Heroku [Article]

## **Teaching Experience**

# **Amar iSchool**

Dhaka, Bangladesh Mar, 2021 - Dec, 2021

**Head Course Instructor** 

Applied Data Science and Machine Learning — [Course Repository]

Our prime goal is to empower the local ML enthusiasts with a limited background CS and Mathematics.

- Taught data science and machine learning for production
- Gave 15 lectures, all self-developed
- Developed course assignments and projects

## **Selected Projects**

An exhaustive list can be found here

- (1) Medical Expertise Style Transfer System for Layman Patients PyTorch, Fastai, Flask [Code]
- (2) Multimodal Multi-label Genre Classifier PyTorch, Fastai, Numpy, Pandas [Code]
- (3) Anime vs Animation vs CGI PyTorch, Fastai, Flask [Code]
- (4) Original Transformer for Bengali Translation PyTorch [Code]

### **Skills**

Programming Language: Python, C, C++, Ruby, Octave

Framework: Pytorch, fastai, Flask, Tensorflow, Keras, Ruby on Rails

Tools and Libraries: Git, LaTeX, Google Colab, HuggingFace, Google Cloud Platform

Languages: English, Bangla, Hindi, Arabic

## **Selected Awards & Achievements**

An exhaustive list can be found here

- Won the OIC Scholarship that waived 75% of my undergraduate education costs (2% acceptance rate)
- Champion, 2nd Nurse Care Activity Recognition Challenge 2020. Won a trip to Japan. [P1]
- Finalist, AI For Bangla Challenge 2021 (among 147 teams) [P3]
- Runners Up, IUT Computer Programming Contest 2019 (among 77 teams)
- 2nd Runners Up, EDU Inter University Programming Contest 2020 (among 50 teams)

## **Extra-curricular Activities**

- Travelled across major locations in Bangladesh.
- Part of ML Discussion Groups: Fordham DS Research Group, Turing NLP Group
- Associate Member, Omdena AI Global Community
- Contest Judge, 16th December Programming Contest 2019
- Former Programming Instructor, IUT Programming Community
- Former Vice President, IUT Computer Society
- Assistant General Secretary, IUT 10th ICT Fest
- Volunteer Coordinator, IUT 9th ICT Fest
- Class and Batch Representative, IUT CSE Batch'16

#### References

Available upon request